Welcome to Strolling,
conversations with people.
I meet along the way.
I'm Rosano here with Judy Perly, owner
of Toronto's Free times cafe, which
has been serving authentic Jewish and
middle Eastern food for over 40 years
while also functioning as a hub for
folk music in the city, with live shows
during the week and a songwriter open
stage that's been running for decades.
What struck me from our exchange
was her spirit of usefulness,
curiosity and freedom at 71 years.
the connections between
everything become apparent with
her holistic view of the world.
Making it effortless to jump from
food, to art, to politics, to life.
Despite recording at the tail end of an
exhausting day, her presence with me was
lively, generous, and sharp as a knife.
It's a privilege to have
Judy as my first guest.
So without further ado, let's get into it.
judy, welcome to the podcast
and thanks for being here.
Oh, thank you.
What do most people know you for?
They know me as the owner of free
times cafe on college street,
no me for other things too.
Like, you know, my yoga friends know me as
a yogini and people know me from part of
a group of people that swim, swim lengths.
People who live in my condo, normally
it's this woman who owns a restaurant.
My identity and the present is from my
well-known business free times cafe.
And I'm known as the local yid
in downtown Toronto, the one
that represents Jewish culture.
Right, And it's been like that for awhile.
I imagined.
Yeah.
For like 25 years the Jewish
part and on the free times for
like over 40 years, 40 years.
Yeah.
And where are you at right now?
What do you mean?
Where am I at?
After 40 years, what do you do?
Do you just shut it down?
Like I emote, every day
I rant about something.
I conceptualize I try to see
the world in a bigger picture.
I don't agree with most of
the status quo of things.
I worry about the state of the
world and very concerned in the bill
of goods is been sold to people.
What's the bill of goods?
The bill of goods is this
fearful negative view of life.
This limiting negative view of life.
And COVID is just a symptom of that.
And that was just part of his
ongoing negative view, which
started when I was young.
And I was a teacher in that.
And I left teaching when I was 26 because
I found the system so hypocritical
weren't really interested in teaching.
The main topic of conversation in
the staff room was the pension,
the mortgage, and the racist jokes.
And I always wanted more.
I wanted to be more in this world having
one more authentic life and to be free.
I always strove to feel free.
And, you know, I was an artist and I
wanted to reinvent myself every time.
And I got into cooking and then I
just cooked my way through life.
I was given the gift of cooking.
You've had my food and whatever I cook.
It's good.
And I never know what it's going to be.
The food speaks to me and
tells me what to do with it.
So it sounds like food is not
just a nutritional thing for you.
Like what, what does it
mean ? Is it like a social thing?
Is it like a magical thing?
Is it like a artistic thing?
Like
It's a soul thing for me,  cooking
makes my soul feel good.
You know, when I cook, I feel good if I
don't feel good and I cook, I feel good.
So it's my cure.
It's the cure for my soul.
I  feel people are cooking
at home less and less today.
Do you think that's okay.
Well, it was cold.
People started cooking more, but
they're getting all this prepared
stuff in boxes and it tells you
what to do and this and that.
And I don't necessarily agree with it.
I'm not saying it's entirely
wrong, but cooking is much
easier than people think it is.
Oh, you just need to have a few of
the right utensils, but not too many.
people complicate cooking and
they complicate it with recipes.
I'm somewhat against recipes.
Yea, you convinced me
to stop using recipes.
And that totally changed my relationship
with, I think I became a chef in some
sense, like, because, or I just tell
you that to stop using investigates,
you told me go to the supermarket,
buy whatever you like, take a carrot
and just bite it, just eat it.
Like it just tasted directly.
And then you start to get a sense
of the flavors and the tastes.
And that, that really happened for me.
It was like, oh, okay.
And I totally didn't think that was.
But yeah, it like over time, it's like,
oh, actually I kind of liked that.
I like when it's cut like this,
I like this when it's with that.
Right.
And you don't have to cut
it the same way every time.
And every time when I cook, I don't
necessarily make the things the same.
Like when I make meat sauce, every
time I make it, it's different.
It's not exactly the same.
Why should it be?
Yeah, you see, this is the thing of north
America, where we mass produce things.
The same.
We have this, this idea that
everything has to be the same.
Or it has to be the there's the
expert, the idea of the expert
and the expert has the recipe.
And if you follow the recipe
of the expert, you will have
achieved expertise yourself.
Not true.
It's kind of a new idea.
I guess, though, you can buy experience
or expertise or something like that.
maybe a hundred or two years, a
hundred years ago, like you would
have had to have the experience in
order to achieve a certain thing.
Look, women were cooking for thousands
of years and getting no credit for it.
Every family had a personal chef
and we didn't call it that we
just called it your mother, right.
Some were better than others.
Pretty well every family
had a personal chef.
Think about it in today's world.
It's a rarity that, that, you know,
you're going to get all your meals
cooked by somebody there in the house.
Right.
They might cook some of them.
You, yeah, but some very beautiful
things are done through food.
Food was my, my go-to and it still is.
There was a time in my life
where I was so unhappy.
The only time I was happy
was when I was cooking.
So, you know, cooking as a
therapy is, is, is strong.
I think it's a wonderful thing to do.
I mean, we need to take people with mental
health issues and get them into cooking
and not just in these institutionalized
kitchens, these big kitchens.
No.
Mental health has to be something
in people's homes, you know,
it has to be matched up.
I feel like people don't think about food
is a cure for mental health specifically.
Like how do you see that connection?
Well, the process of
it is very therapeutic.
You know, we're involved
with creating something.
Creation is always satisfying.
And you need to eat your
nourishing yourself, keeping
your energy up good health.
And it's very social.
Somebody who knows how to
cook is going to have friends.
People are going to
want to be around them.
They're going to want
to go to their house.
Maybe if they're not very verbal
or they don't have greatest person.
They can at least cook a meal
and people want to be there.
It's something to offer.
And it's a giving thing.
You're giving it to other people.
You can learn generosity.
But we need to eat to live.
And it's so basic.
We get hungry.
We need to eat.
And if you involve yourself with all
the little bits of food that you have in
your fridge and you create a delicious
meal out of it, this is a work of art.
And it's very satisfying.
We forget that a lot of mental health
issues have nothing to do with our brains.
They have to do with our souls and we
have forgotten what a soul is in this
world, you know, and the soul is not
your body and it's not your brain.
It's the flow of your life in your
brain and your body, it's like
who you are and where you take it.
And it's everything combined.
Everything put together is your soul.
But we've compartmentalized and
we've really killed the soul.
And this is why we have so
many mental health issues.
Because we've lost connection with soul.
Yeah.
Thomas Moore.
Okay.
Not the English writer, but
this is American philosopher.
He said the soul likes small things.
And that sentence changed my life.
So whenever you are unhappy, for
whatever reason, you don't know
why I don't feel good today.
I'm unhappy, I'm anxious.
I'm angry on this.
I'm that.
And you know, you engage in some
small activity like sweeping the floor
or wiping off a table or something.
Just the involvement in that
small activity can sooth the soul.
Women traditionally have been
involved in these mundane acts.
So people talk of their
mothers in a different way than
they do with their fathers.
And they often see their mothers as
having more soul in their fathers.
And I think it's mainly because
the women were relegated to doing
these small tasks and actually in
a way that was their liberation.
You mentioned wanting to be free earlier.
How do you feel today?
Do you feel free?
Yeah, I do pretty free.
Not completely free, but I
feel freer than I've ever felt.
I'd say.
I mean, you have a lot of
things to do every week.
You have a restaurant you're managing it.
Some people would say that's being tied
down or you have commitments or whatever,
but you feel free in spite of all of this.
Yeah.
But having those commitments and
having to get up and go somewhere,
it's just kind of ordinary.
But feeling really free is
something that you earn over time.
You know, that's like clearing out, hiring
the organizer and decluttering, you know,
that's years and years of decluttering.
Well, this is what I mean, because it
seems like you're not talking about some
purely logistical thing of like, having
time, for example, because you don't
really, I mean, you're busy, and I think
that's what people associate with freedom.
It's like, oh, I have the time.
Or maybe I'm like filthy
rich or something like that.
But it means something other
than that, I do have time.
I take time.
Like I take three hours in the morning.
Sometimes I lie in bed for an
hour before I get out of bed.
I take the time to have the time,
have a nice bed in my, in my bed.
I don't clutter my life
is a lot of busy work.
actually in Cove, I felt more free in
many ways because I had my nights free and
didn't have to relate to so many people.
It was so nice to come home and cook
dinner for myself every night and have
all this delicious and then to give it
to others That's one, one part of it,
you know, doing yoga, hired my yoga
teacher, two classes of yoga for like the
last year and a bed that's been amazing.
But feeling free is a state of being,
you know, it's not a situation.
The only thing that would drive me crazy
would be,  I could be locked up in a
room, but noise would drive me crazy, like
constant, loud rock music or a constant
loud noise that would drive me crazy.
Or if I have to eat really awful
food, all that would be hard.
But if it was very plain food, I would
be okay with it, like real food that was
playing, like, let's say plain boiled
potatoes, what's awful, you know, packaged
food phones, you know, commercial,
food, commercial food, the chemicals.
It's not really food.
What are you close minded about?
Ooh, close minded about,  I think I'm
close minded about people who aren't,
risk-takers, too careful in their lives.
I've talked with that.
Close minded about people who
are in relationships for ulterior
motives, like for money or for
status people that use other pupil.
I'm pretty close minded about
materialistic people to the extreme.
Not that I don't like things, I do.
Not that I don't have friends that will
spend lots of money, uncles, but people
who are not generous, I'm pretty close
minded about people who are selfish.
It's interesting that you're always
referencing people as opposed to some
kind of ideology or a school of thought
or something, or just a way to, oh yeah.
Cool.
Yeah.
I'm pretty closed minded about,
letting people starve, and out and
wars I'm completely against wars.
Letting people starve has something to do
with food waste for you also, other than,
you know,  taking care of one another.
I mean, it seems like a topic that all
absolutely shameful and we're the worst
culprits in the world, north America.
Yeah.
But there's no penalty on it.
Well, whatever, you know, there's
no penalty for food waste, We waste
by 40% of all food, but I'm not
talking about dumpster diving either.
I'm not in favor of dumpster diving.
Not that I would say
judge people who do it.
Cause I can understand doing, I
really can, but the fact that we put
all this food in the dumpster, in
the first place, that's the problem.
Right.
In this whole, before due date, things
is an artificial manufacturer because
that was just a way to move more product.
It's not necessarily that.
Oh yeah, yeah.
Actually we just did that so they could
keep the shelves full and somebody could
buy it and it was still last at home.
So they would just take the stuff that was
two or three days and just throw it up.
You know, now people are getting
interested in these best before last day
and then people are buying them more and
more because food is expensive, but we
got to stop this wastage and selfishness
around food and extravagance around food.
Right?
Yeah.
That everything has to be fancy
that we eat, you know, that you
can't eat rice and beans and
simple food and feel good about it.
Not that I eat that much rice and
beans, but at my age is not maybe
the best food for me to be eating.
And I'm very pissed about
bad health being the norm.
No.
I'm very pissed that of all the money that
comes into Ontario spent on healthcare.
So if you had a family doing that,
let's say the family earned a hundred
thousand dollars a year and they
spent 60,000 of it on healthcare.
You say, well, what's wrong.
What's wrong with you?
There's something wrong here.
Why are you spending $60,000 in any base?
Barely have money for food,
housing and everything else?
Well, this is, this is our society
and the way we treat elders and in
many ways, the way we treat children,
micro-managing them imprisoning them.
I think I'm against the norm of
society, the norms of society.
I think everyone liked the
norm and I hate the Cove norm.
I think it's a  bill of goods that has
been sold to people and the problem
coves spread because of inherent social
problems that we had before COVID started.
It's like tuberculosis.
There were social problems that
existed that spread to tuberculosis.
Lack of proper housing damn
posing, cold housing, no heat.
That's what spread tuberculosis.
The way we treat our elders, the
way we treat immigrants, the way
we treat people who worked in
factories, that's what spread.
Oh, okay.
The conditions by which we
force these people to live under
created a certain kind of outcome.
Okay.
And also their immune system
being worn down from eating
crappy food, not taken by him.
There's nobody ever wants on TV,
talked about keeping your immune
system strong to prevent getting Cove.
So what is a human being?
What is our bottom line about being human?
That's what, the questions that we
have to ask . So I'm a hypocrite.
I don't say my true feelings all the
time because I can't, but I do  with
my staff . And they agree with me.
I tell them, they're lucky.
They're lucky.
I'm not crazy.
Okay.
I remember in the height of Cove, I
went to the island with my girlfriend
and I put my purse on the ground.
She says, don't, it could get cold.
I've got a sidewalk.
How was it going to live on a sidewalk?
You tell me.
Anyway, so what is that time you is
telling you that there is this inherent
fear that we've all been brought up
with that was there before COVID.
Why was I not afraid?
Because I was very lucky.
I was somewhat neglected and brought
up in laneways on a main street and the
1950s and sixties and allowed to run free.
And I had a father who was
a free spirit and a outlier.
I didn't believe in the status
quo and taught me how to think.
And the other thing is that we all
have to accept is nobody cares.
In the end, you better do it for
yourself because nobody's going to care.
They will try to care.
And when you seek help, you may get it.
But for your core life,
you better do a future.
You're saying society as a
whole doesn't care about you.
Yeah.
Like you have to take care of yourself.
Yeah, our society helps a little bit, but
they, with one hand they take it away.
And the other hand they give it to you.
I feel like . Look at Rosano traveling
around the world in the last five years.
You made the money to take
care of yourself to do it.
You had your way of looking at the world.
You made your connections in
the way that you wanted to . you
didn't look to the government of
Canada to make it happen for you.
I kind of feel like my situation was
a consequence of like the freedom that
I had to not live in society as it is.
But that is the gift of a middle-class
upbringing and an education.
You did in the right way.
And I did too in that we were
not particularly materialistic.
So that's the real gift of a
civilized societies to give
people individual freedom.
We talk about that, but in fact, we're not
doing that because we're molding people
into consumers who value materialism and
are full of fear and they're not brave.
And they haven't gone out there in
the world and done it themselves
and created that really core
confidence and be ready to die.
I don't give a shit if I die.
I'm afraid of a bad accident and,
and having horrific injuries from a
bad accident, I'm not afraid to die.
I could die to the world, so I've
lived my life, but I'm afraid if
I had a horrible accident, that
would be much worse than dying.
What are you afraid of?
You think about that?
I feel like I worry a lot, but
I don't know if that's because
I'm afraid necessarily, or maybe
I'm just being paranoid, but like
really genuinely fear full of stuff.
What do you worry about?
I'm constantly, I don't know
this is going to work out.
I don't know if I have
enough money after the year.
I don't know what's going to happen
if I don't figure this thing out.
I'm not going to have
to go on unemployment.
It's, it's actually, it's a lot of
materialistic things, maybe lower chakra.
It was lower chakra, very low chakra.
within us, we have so much power.
Our society is just so narrow considering,
but I have hope for the future.
I have hope for younger people,
and I have hope for women.
I think, you know, women are going
to come up really strong in a good.
And men, you know, if the, if
the men are smart, they will too,
but you know, men have been sold
a bill of goods, unfortunately,
and are still believing in that.
You should take a break, you know, let us
do the heavy lifting, take a break guys.
I think that, you know,
smart families did that.
You guys took a break.
And these realizations, a part of what
you call the gift of getting older.
You have hope all of a sudden or… oh, I
always was an optimistic person because
I've actually used so many things.
I've made so many things happen.
I mean, initiated 12,000 cultural events.
And… Twelve thousand?
Yea that's what Free Times
has had 12,000 over 12,000.
Right.
I invented this fantastic brunch that
happened every week for 26 years.
I had an art career,
I've done tons of art.
And so I've done things, but I was that
type of person, you know, I did a lot of
what I did because I was very unhappy.
And if it didn't do
things,  I couldn't function.
You know, in today's where we just
drug people up, you just give them a
tranquilizers and whatever, if they're
not unhappy and it, and it disables them.
And that, that's also the core
of our problems, too many drugs.
Not that I don't drink alcohol
and I don't have a puff, but it's
not like all day, every day, the
society just lets addiction go on.
They let addiction go on until it's
it's total crisis where I've been
dealing with the core issue, which
is that we all love people be free.
I'm happy to see marriages not
happening as frequently as they used to.
It's a good thing.
Because as far as I'm concerned,
a marriage should be: what the
five-year term you want the 10
year term five removed, renewable.
Okay.
Right.
Should it be like, yeah,
like a mortgage, right?
This whole idea that you're going to
meet with one person for your whole
life creates happiness for some,
but a lot of distress for others.
You might say removes freedom
for a bunch of people.
Most people, think people think
there's something wrong with changing.
To be free to change music, you have
to maybe admit that you made a mistake
or something, but it's not a mistake.
I think in the old days,
it was very hard to change.
People lived in this class based
society and you couldn't really
move through the classes where you
were born, was really going to stay.
And, I remember my brother telling
me in the middle ages, the average
person never went further than five
kilometers from where they were born.
and Canada pre world war two was like
60, 70% rural farmers was a country
full of farmers was, was, but still
is your, you know, your Canadians who
have roots for generations are farmers.
I want to ask you a little bit about
tech because I find it so curious
that someone from your generation
just  seems to adapt so well to it.
And you have your contacts in your
iPhone, and you're always like
calling people and use social media.
And we could talk about
your vine Starbucks.
I see.
That's the thing with me is that
I think I'm terrible attack now.
How old are you again?
71 71.
Okay.
Took me two years to download an app.
I was so afraid to download an app.
I would never do it.
I still require help to do things.
Okay.
But I seek help.
This is the other thing.
I understand how to process things
that you need people to teach you how
to do things, but there's a learning
curve, but a lot of people think
that you should just be able to pick
it up and know how to do it yet.
But maybe from that generation of
my generation needs to be taught.
And because it's not formalized
in our society is like
marriage and having children.
And I found nobody's formally
taught how to use an iPhone.
So I'd have to say people who
use it, don't know how to use it.
Especially from my generation
where it's not intuitive.
It's not just for your
generation, but sure.
Yeah.
But I was also forced because
of the requirements of my work.
I like it because it's so much easier,
but that's the thing , you enjoy it
ultimately and you're, you're taking
to it and you find your own way to
sort of express yourself through it.
And it's not like, uh, uh, it's another
new thing I got to like, you, you embrace
it more or less cause it's obviously like
a completely different social pattern.
Like, um, I work with
wedding younger people.
So they'd teach me like you,
You are responsible for my vine stardom.
It's all your fault Rosano!
You were famous, you became a celebrity.
And that was my fault.
I take full you and Jessie.
It was totally random.
Remember you sitting across to me St.
Judy, I'm going to put this in
your phone, have some fun with it.
So I said, right.
Yeah.
It was you, you see the
power that you have.
Yeah.
It's interesting.
I mean, so you became, one of your
videos went viral totally by chance.
And then you had this following
of like 10, 15,000 people.
Mostly like, yeah.
I didn't try.
If I had tried, I could've gotten away up.
Could have worked it.
I never worked it.
I think a lot of people, if they
find that kind of success, they will
try to grip onto it for dear life.
And you're sort of like, you
know, vine isn't around anymore.
Fine is vine is gone.
Now maybe people who are listening
don't even know what vine is.
It used to be this, but she
knows that somebody actually
tattooed on their bum Judy.
Oh my gosh.
Yeah.
That's dedication the
dedication of your fans.
Yeah.
Most people would, would
want to like, keep it going.
And so now there's tic talk, which is
kind of the thing that would, when you
used to do and you don't want to do that.
You're like, no, well, I'm kind of done
with that part of my life and you're not.
I don't feel like it.
And what, how do you
arrive at that conclusion?
To not have even the curiosity?
Because I'm onto other things.
You're onto other things?
I'd rather be on a dating app
and exploring that as characters
and just move on to other things.
There's lots of other
things in this world.
Why keep doing the same
thing over and over?
my life is very varied and I worked
as varied and I'm not a hyper person.
Like I don't have to be
doing things all the time.
Right.
I enjoy having two or three hours
a day of not doing anything much.
I let enjoy sitting, thinking
you actually sit and think.
Yeah, well, I enjoy thinking
more than anything really.
And I talk a lot and I philosophize a lot.
A lot of people, Mike keeps, Mike
keeps track of Judaism's Judaism.
I think.
What do I think about, I think
about what's real and what isn't.
What's real?
Many things are real.
I think about the things that don't
appear to be real, but really are real.
Like?
Just being in your physical self.
The body?
The body and such.
affection that's real.
Loving Feelings are real.
Food is real.
And What's not real?
The suburbs, aren't real malls.
Aren't real.
I have a hard time with all that stuff.
Why aren't they real?
Cause they're a construct.
They're an artificial
materialistic construct.
I have a hard time with them.
I have a lot of moralism around it.
It seems like it's just, people
well know that there is kind of
a kind of a goal I guess, bombed
behind, but I don't like the suburbs.
I think dehumanizes people and not to
say that there aren't real and good
and interesting people who live in the
suburbs, but I think most of them would
rather not be living in the suburbs.
They do that because they
don't have other options.
It's not a choice, right.
It's not a choice.
Especially immigrants.
Most of the centers are started by
immigrants, most would rather live in
a livable city where they came from.
But unfortunately that part of their lives
has been destroyed because some dominant
country made war and they became refugees.
It's not a good thing.
It's an awful thing.
All of this reflection on what's real.
And what's not real.
You think about it within
yourself, I'm guessing.
But, you mentioned once, like
wanting to start a therapy
practice to like help other people.
So you want to also like bring this
out to other people and help them
realize, like, how do you see your,
how do you imagine yourself doing that?
Well, you know, like a lot of things
I've done in my life, my life in
many ways has been very random.
It's like a vine.
Like I, I only see it really happening in
a situation like I was needed to do it.
Well, you can get a business card and
have a shtick and be like, no, it's
just, I do it with people anyways.
Like I do it with my staff.
I give them these front characters
that they can hide behind
and you know, they feel a lot
better about their insecurities.
Can you give some examples?
Well, you know, I'm Ms.
Critical, critical.
Yeah.
Tiffany is Ms.
Overconfident.
Mike's.
Mr.
Nice guy, Ravi is Mr.
Do it myself, Sandra.
And is Mr.
Speedo?
Katie is Ms.
Apologetic,  when we're stressed,
we go to these characters that
are not always our best selves.
So when our not so best selves
come out, we can say, it's this
other self that's doing it.
We don't have to identify,
be a little more forgiving.
We don't have to identify our
wholesales and the staff have
found that really helpful.
Your stuff finds it helpful because
they can check in on and I'll say
that to Tiffany in it potentially
stressing situation, I'll say how's Ms.
Overconfident.
Is she bothering you or is
she, you know, taking over?
Oh no, Judy, I think she's under control.
And what is Rosano's cover?
And how many do I have?
Oh, maybe one in every country
you go to that's lovely, shy guy.
Mr.
Shy guy.
I'm I'm less shy than I was.
So he's kind of going way.
what's the name for the person
who's thinking of the, think
he thinks of you in the head.
well, yeah, you're reborn, but you all,
it's hard for you to gain presence.
Oh, okay.
So Mr.
I'm not here you're kind of like Mr.
I'm not here when stressed, you know,
like you disappear, So that's also why
you move from country to country because
like, you know, disappearing and moving
to another place and then reestablishing
yourself and then kind of disappear
and you're, but you are very spiritual.
You do flow on this magic carpet.
I think you're an amazing person.
I really do, but you're still reacting.
You're still not completely yourself,
but you're getting there for your age.
You're doing really well.
Thank you, that's very generous.
Yeah, yeah.
Mr.
Disappearing is always
happy when he is grounded.
So he needs grounding.
Okay.
I love this.
And I'm wondering if it works in
the other direction also where the
thing that you want to be has a name.
So that's a good one.
It would be Mr.
B here.
Now something like the sir or well,
for each of your staff or whoever.
You know what, I think
what you want to be Mr.
Lover?
I could be Mr.
Lover.
I could, I could want to be Mr.
I think that's what you are
that you want to be, you know,
a lover, in your body lover.
I think I want to be Ms.
Not nice guy, but be a
nice person all the time.
Really?
You want to be that that's shocking to me.
Cause I thought you would have been
sick of that or you deliberately try
not to do that because you've targeted,
like trying to please other people
or something, but you want that.
Yeah.
I'd like to be at peace.
Ms.
Peaceful, maybe.
Nice guy, but in a real
way, be kind to people.
I find it sometime really hard
to be kind I have the sharp wit.
I know it has not been easy for you to
be out there in the world on your own,
maybe worried about the next dollar
that you're going to make, or where
are you going to sleep that night or
whatever, putting yourself out there.
But you knew that you had to
do that because if you didn't
do it, the consequences were
worse than the other direction.
And what were the consequences
going to be mental health issues.
You had to fight for your life in a
different way because the society tries
to take it away from you in every term.
Somehow you were given that strength.
Like I was to be able to do that and
say, no, I'm not going to have this free
conscribed life or work for the man worked
for the company and, you know, work on my
computer from home and never go anywhere.
Yeah.
I was encouraged by a good friend of mine.
He was doing.
Pushing me to like buy one of those
backpacks that I can just keep everything
in there and I don't have to hold
anything in my hand and I can walk around.
It took him  few years maybe of trying
to prod me to try traveling out.
It was very recently, but
it happened because of
encouragement of people that came.
And also people like yourself,
encourage me to do my own thing, be
myself, so to speak , these cliches.
But it's meant a lot of , very
profound experiences for me.
And I've learned a lot about myself
and I've had a kind of life that
not a lot of people get to have.
And so I'm super grateful about that.
but yeah, I, I don't feel, I can
totally take credit for that.
I did put in the work and I did do it,
but , I also just want to acknowledge
like the people that, oh yeah.
I mean, it's the same with me too,
because all the thousands of wonderful
people I've met and worked with, but
ultimately you're the center of it.
And you're the center of your world.
You're the one who pushes the button.
That's why I'm saying, that's
why I say, nobody cares.
You got to do it.
That's what I mean by that.
And then ultimately it's your
decision whether you do or you don't
.
Our society is a very
sick oriented society.
We use sickness as a cop-out that's
always the reason not to do, oh,
I'm this I'm that .  When we get
sick as a reason not to do not
to love, be disappointed in love.
So you get sick.
Sometimes you die.
Not to fight against what your parents
want . So you get sick, you get depressed.
Your will is broken.
The best thing a parent could do for
their child is not to break their will.
We're born with a will, but it can be
broken and society is there to break it.
That's actually, unfortunately the, dark
side of society is to break our Wells so
that we do what society wants us to do.
Why do you think people get
taken in by these scammers?
Wow.
This was the CRA a calling.
They told me that I had a package
of illegal things and that
it was going to be arrested.
Right.
Do you know what I say to them?
Because I always go to the number one.
So the answer.
And the citizen.
Does your mother know that
you're a scammer is not the best?
And how did they respond to that?
Usually they hang up at one
time, a woman said, no, well
said, well, you should tell her.
She should know what you're doing.
How you cheating Canadians
out of their money.
And I hung up.
I'm trying to imagine what it's like
for them to treat them as human beings.
They are human beings.
They are.
Yes.
But, and it's almost that it's, that
you've actually like for one you've
acknowledged her humanity, which she's
probably not, she's literally, uh, well
presenting themselves as bots or robots
or whatever, but then also to just
like to come into her situation there,
which no nobody's going to do that.
So I'm, I'm trying to put myself in
that person's shoes, just like, what's
it like to receive that from, from
Judy, from, you know, from somebody
in north America, will we need to
confront them on a human level that
these are people that they're calling.
We are not just stick figures on our money
is not there because it was given to us.
Is that easy for you to
just speak to somebody?
Very easy, because I think, and I can
also be really nasty on the phone when,
when these places call at the restaurant.
I'll say, Nope, the owner died.
We're just folding up the
restaurant now kind of story.
But I mostly get to the mother thing,
and how do you know that that's a thing?
Cause I know it's a thing,
especially with third world
people, a mother is everything.
Mother is the judge of the morality.
The keeper or the morals of the
family is really the mother more than
the father in terms of their child.
I think the father keeps the
morals of the outside world, but
the mother really keeps the family
morals in bringing up the child.
The kid on a daily basis has to deal
with the mother on the big issues.
Maybe the father, but on the daily
basis, the mother knows what's going on.
What would it sound like if I said,
does your father know what you're doing?
Does your mother know what you're doing?
What's the difference?
Does your mother know you're a scammer?
Does your father know you're a scammer?
What sounds worse?
To me anyway, it feels more emotional.
Yeah.
It's more emotional.
Canadians don't have the same quite
strong relationship with the mother.
And also the power of women in the family
is not as respected in Canadian cultures.
It doesn't, let's say Sri Lankan
culture or Indian culture.
Right.
The mother the boss, right?
Chinese.
See, we have diminished
the matriarchal here.
It's part of our problem, That's why
we have to have women's lib, because
we so weaken women into  nothingness.
put them in the suburbs to
give anything away from them.
And they didn't even have to cook anymore.
Just open up packages and then took
all the power, which is terrible.
Well, when you put it like that.
Are you recording all this one?
My God.
That's great.
Don't tell them.
It's me tell them it's somebody else.
Judy recorded this, play it.
When I croak, just come to my funeral.
Everybody who's listening to this.
You're invited to my funeral.
I'm 71.
I'm gonna live to be 102 to 31 years.
Come to my funeral.
I need 10,000 people and it's going to
be a big party and I'm going to be thrown
into the ocean in a mermaid cop coffin.
I'm going out like a mermaid.
I'm not going to be buried in the ground.
I went to a funeral last year and
I saw the cold or this little,
you know, this little  piece,
so small and just stuck in it.
Who wants to be there?
I don't want to be in the ocean.
It's taken me away.
Take me away.
Did you get that idea from somewhere?
Is that your creative thing?
I was a scuba diver.
So I have experienced the underwater
and, and also some of the most  extent
at times of my life underwater.
And because I've been swimming every
week for like 45 years, I have a strong
relationship with the water and I saw a
movie on women who want to be mermaids,
who mermaid costumes and go down to
the beach and lie on the sand and their
mermaid costumes, which I'm hoping to
be able to do at some point in my life.
So why not?
Right.
I think my generation is going to
have very creative funerals and I'd
say that a good business to get into
would be deterred shaped coffins.
I heard a chair first get in on
the ground floor guitar shaped
coffins, or shaped coffins, right?
I'd say half the men in my generation are
going to want to be buried in a guitar
because of the electric guitar fender.
They all see themselves as artists.
I've been exploring the feminine,
the masculine what's the feminine
about feminine's very beautiful,
very deep, so it's masculine.
but you know, we all have
both sides to ourselves.
We need not be afraid of those sides,
but I also know that we do gain our
main orientation from the opposite sex.
women, gain their deep femininity
from men and men gain their
deep masculinity from women.
from a relationship with a woman,
you will get the feeling of being
a man, not from another man.
The deep feeling of being a
man, you will get a surface.
Let's say the father gets
you to join a team sport.
Okay.
I'm one of the boys.
And then the team, that's
like a surface man, but the
deep man comes from the woman.
What's a deep Deep man is the
man who pleases a woman who truly
pleases a woman is a deep man.
And the deep woman is the
one who can be pleased.
The one who can be pleased can be
pleased Who let's the man please her.
Ms.
Surrenders gives herself the
permission to enjoy it's right.
I think that's what
all sexuality is about.
Is it though surrendering
and dominating surrendering?
Unfortunately in our society
is so repressed that it comes
out in a lot of pornography.
which isn't necessarily a bad thing.
It's only a bad thing
because it becomes obsessive.
That's actually a big illness in
our society because people's natural
sexuality has been denied that it's
not interwoven into our ceremonies and
mentor, social being, it's kind of hidden.
It's always like the dark side.
Clandestine?
Yeah.
Have you watched Goop?
Goop?
The Gwyneth Paltrow documentary
dynamometry or it's like a
Netflix series about sex.
A bunch of different couples come
together and Gwyneth Paltrow is going to
put them together with a therapist and
they're going to try and improve each
couple's sex life in a different way.
Cause it's a couple of different
issues that they're struggling with.
It's a lot of relationship with body.
Healthier relationships towards
the body towards sexuality.
They even had an elderly couple there,
sort of a taboo thing or something elderly
in their mind, they use the word elderly.
Um, but those people were maybe in their
sixties or seventies, so they used the
word elderly, Rosa, I consider you mature.
I consider you an elder elder,
but not elderly elder though.
No, I consider you young actually.
You're, you're quite useful, you know?
you ride a bike and you got a hula hoop
thing going sometimes, and you're a hippie
and then you leave your door unlocked
and you put your, but I still don't lock.
You don't lock your door.
You have just, don't tell them where
I, I won't tell anybody I do it.
I only do it when, like, I go away, you
know, like going out to town or something,
but that doesn't happen too often.
Or if there's workmen around, you know,
like if there's people around and it
was a low strangest around, I will walk.
Yeah.
There's people   who don't
live here essentially.
Yeah.
I just don't want to lock my door.
I don't want to get
locked out of my own home.
Isn't that crazy?
It seems like there's this parallel
between the coffin, like not
being, wanting to be in a box and
locked in a box around freedom.
My total.
Yeah.
I'm always doing practices of
liberation, liberation, and also true.
We need to practice these things.
We need to put ourselves in a
situation where we might lose and
see what happens you certainly have.
And how has that matured you?
Oh, uh, it's been fantastic.
I wouldn't trade it for anything.
if you'd stayed in the normal society, you
wouldn't have gained all this insight and
confidence that you've gotten from Lucy.
Right.
You've had things stolen from you.
Actually.
I haven't, I haven't been
pretty lucky in that.
I haven't really had much to say except
from the police, but, um, but other
than that, no, I mean, I've, I've
surprised myself because I'm sort of new
to traveling and this idea of staying
in  strangers' homes and, uh, whether
it's Airbnb or couch surfing or friend
of a friend or whatever, but like,
I've always just trusted the person
and I've never like, lost anything.
So I've been really fortunate
in that respect for it.
And I've stayed in like a
lot of other people's places.
it's like almost something should've
happened by now, but, um, no, I mean, I
I've been very fortunate, but also there's
so much to be gained from just accepting
that good things happen from randomness.
Like you can't always control everything.
I think, you know, we say we don't
want to take the risk, but what is
the risk on the other side in terms of
your social self and your soul self.
I want to ask you another thing
about tech cause again, I find it
so curious that someone from your
era is in this present today, which
is so hyper-connected and mobile.
Is there something you wish people
would carry over from like the older
kinds of media that you grew up with?
I don't know, TV, radio,
newspaper, whatever.
Because now we have all these new patterns
and it's very fast and very instantaneous.
Is there something  from  older technology
that you would like to see represented?
Oh, well, I think of new technology
more than old, my fantasy is that
we'll have chips implanted in
our fingers for various things.
And one of them is going to be our
computer implant and that we touched
the table and that becomes so computer.
So you're looking more into the
future and you want to see this?
I told all the old stuff
is already in there.
Isn't it?
I mean, you have, this is a podcast radio.
Well, I'm not actually asking, I'm
not asking about the technology.
I mean like the way you would interact
with people, maybe there are certain
ways of interacting with people that are
maybe no longer present and maybe that
could have been good or maybe not, you
know, and maybe the way we do things
now, sort of asynchronously and short
messages and or not handwritten or not.
Do you miss anything?
I think the ways of communicating
now are so varied and exciting.
I think it's fantastic.
Like all communicate with
different people in different ways.
It's excitement, instant messaging,
WhatsApp, texting, telephone.
Audio message.
FaceTime, face time,
audio message pictures.
So it's exciting for you.
It's stimulating.
Very exciting.
But I think the hardware it's tricky
because you don't want to lose your phone.
Right.
I think we, we, we need to
have chips embedded in us.
I don't want to have keys anymore.
I don't want to have hardware anymore.
We should have it in us and we've touched
surfaces and that becomes our hardware.
Wow.
I'm not even there yet.
I need, that's just my fantasy.
How that could actually happen.
Oh, I don't doubt that
that's going to happen.
I mean, I think that's totally reasonable.
Where can people find out
more about what you're doing?
What's your free times come to the
free times, restaurant three 20
colors street, Toronto, two free times
Anything else you want to mention?
okay, so this is my advice to all of
you, the three prong approach to problem
solving delay, as long as possible, get
more information, get more information,
look where you are for the answer.
It's usually right in front of you.
Amazing.
Thanks so much for being with me Judy.
Namaste.
That was my extended conversation
with Judy Perly on the
first episode of strolling.
Thanks for being a member and helping keep
this podcast independent and sustainable.
Find links, show notes and Judy's
playlist of five handpicked songs
at strolling dot rosano dot C A.
That's strolling dot R O S A N O dot C A.
Be welcome to leave a comment
on the website or by sending an
email to strolling@rosano.ca.
The music for this episode was
inspired by love at the free
times cafe by norm hacking.
And dance me to the end
of love by Leonard Cohen.
Hope you enjoyed that.
Thanks for listening
and see you next time.